A Guide to the Papers of Peter Hillsman Taylor, 1948-1977
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Peter Hillsman Taylor 1948-1977
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10265,-b
This collection consists of ca. 900 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the Library by Peter Hillsman Taylor of Charlottesville, Virginia, on December 19, 1977, and October 21, 1980.
Biographical/Historical Information
Peter Hillsman Taylor (1917-1994) was born in Trenton, Tennessee, on January 8, 1917. He attended Vanderbilt University (1936-1937), Southwestern at Memphis (1937-1938) and received an A.B. degree from Kenyon College in 1940. Taylor served in the United States Army from 1941 until 1945 and reached the rank of sergeant. He married Eleanor Lilly Ross on June 4, 1943 and they had two children: Katherine Baird Taylor and Peter Ross Taylor.
Taylor was a professor of English at the University of North Carolina at Greensboro (1946-1967); in 1967, he moved to the University of Virginia, where he remained for the rest of his life. Taylor was a visiting lecturer and teach of creative writing at Indiana University (1949), University of Chicago (1951), Kenyon College (1952-1957), Oxford University (1955), Ohio State University (1957-1963), Harvard University (1964 and 1972-1973), and University of Georgia (1985).
In 1956, Taylor was offered a position in The New Yorker's editorial offices which he declined in order to continue teaching. He received a Guggenheim fellowship in fiction in 1950; a National Institute of Arts and Letters grant in literature, 1952; a Fulbright fellowship to France, 1955; first prize, O. Henry Memorial Awards, 1959, for short story Venus, Cupid, Folly and Time; the Ohioana Book Award, 1960, for Happy Families Are All Alike; Ford Foundation fellowship, to England, 1961; Rockefeller Foundation grant, 1964; second prize, Partisan Review-Dial for short story The Scoutmaster; National Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters gold medal for literature, 1979; Ritz Paris Hemingway Award and PEN/Faulkner Award for fiction, both 1986, and Pulitzer Prize for fiction, 1987, all for A Summons to Memphis. He was a member of the National Institute of Arts and Letters and the American Academy of Arts and Sciences.
Taylor's publications include the novels A Woman of Means (1950), A Summons to Memphis (1986) and In the Tennessee Country (1994). His collections of short stories include A Long Fourth and Other Stories (1948), The Widows of Thornton (1954), Happy Families Are All Alike (1959), Miss Leonora When Last Seen and Fifteen Other Stories (1963), The Collected Stories of Peter Taylor (1969), In the Miro District and Other Stories (1977), The Old Forest and Other Stories (1985), and The Oracle at Stoneleigh Court (1993). He was a contributor of stories to numerous anthologies, including The Best American Short Stories, (1945-1946, 1950, 1959-1961, 1965); Prize Stories of 1950: The O. Henry Awards (1950); The Literature of the South (1952); Stories from the Southern Review (1953); Prize Stories 1959: The O. Henry Awards (1959); Prize Stories 1961: The O. Henry Awards (1961); Prize Stories 1965: The O. Henry Awards (1965); and The Sense of Fiction (1966).
Peter Hillsman Taylor died of pneumonia, November 2, 1994, in Charlottesville, Virginia.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of ca. 900 items (9 Hollinger boxes, ca. 3 linear shelf feet), 1948-1977, papers of author Peter Hillsman Taylor. Included in the collection are manuscripts and typescripts of Taylor's books (collections of short stories and plays), short stories, plays, and poetry; galley and page proofs; notbooks containing manuscripts for plays and poetry; correspondence; magazine articles about Taylor and others; and photographs. Many of the manuscripts are for short stories which were first published in The New Yorker. The typed manuscript for Randall Jarrell's "A Sad Heart in the Supermarket" and proofs of his children's story "The Animal Family" are also present.
Taylor's correspondence is primarily of a personal nature but does contain some professional correspondence with Katherine S. White and Robert Angell of The New Yorker; Robert Giroux of Harcourt, Brace, Inc.; and David McDowell of Random House, Inc. and McDowell, Obolensky. Other correspondents include Allen Tate, John Casey, Allen Williamson, John Malcolm Brinnan, Paul Engle, and Ralph Ellison (form letter only). Electrostatic copies of Burt Britton's collection of artists' self portraits, inlucding Eudora Welty, Lillian Hellman, Saul Bellow, and Tennessee Williams, are located at the end of the correspondence.
Also present are magazine articles on Katherine Anne Porter and Peter Taylor from Potomac, the weekly magazine of the Washington Post, and copies of the Kenyon College literary magazine, Hika, from 1939 to 1940, when Taylor was on the staff. An autographed snapshot of Katherine Anne Porter completes the colletion.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into five series: I. Manuscripts, II. Corrrespondence, III. Printed Material, IV. Photographs, and V. Miscellaneous Material. The manuscripts are sub-divided into short stories, plays, poetry, notebooks, and miscellaneous. Within each of these divisions, items are arranged alphabetically by title. Manuscripts for books that are collections of short stories or plays are placed at the ends of their respective sections. The correspondence section is divided into personal correspondence, business correspondence, and correspondence and papers from a year spent in Europe. Taylor's correspondence with The New Yorker, as well as his correspondence with publishing houses, has been separated from his miscellaneous business letters. Printed material, photographs, and miscellaneous material are filed at the end of the collection. All of the material within these latter sections is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Subseries A. Short Stories
    - "After the Theatre" n.d., AMs. 5 pp. (Box 1)
    - "After the Theatre" n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 36 pp. (Box 1)
    - "Annie Sue" n.d., AMs (incomplete). 3 pp. (Box 1)
    - ["Annie Sue"] n.d., TMs (incomplete). 21 p. (Box 1)
    - "Annie Sue" n.d., TMss (w/autograph corrections). 31 p. (Box 1)
    - "Blood" n.d., AMs (incomplete). 2 pp. (Box 1)
    - "The Captain's Son, (originally titled "Patterns" or "Change of Venue" n.d., 2 TMss (w/autograph corrections, 1 electrostatic copy). 59 pp. (Box 1)
    - "A Cheerful Disposition" n.d., Clipping (electrostatic copy). 23 pp. (Box 1)
    - "Cousins, Family Love, Family Life, All That" 1958 Dec 17, Galley Proofs (2 copies). 68 pp. (Box 1)
    - "Cousins, Family Love, Family Life, All That," from The New Yorker 1959 Apr 25, Magazine clipping. 8 pp. (Box 1)
    - "Daphne's Lover" n.d., Clipping (electrostatic copy, w/autograph corrections). 26 pp. (Box 1)
    - "Dean of Men" n.d., TMs (electrostatic copy). 36 pp. (Box 1)
    - "The Elect" 1966 Nov 28, TMs (w/autograph corrections). 17 pp. (Box 1)
    - "A Fable of Nashville" 1975 Aug 19, 3 TMss (incomplete, w/autograph corrections). 15 pp. (Box 1)
    - "Guest," and TLS, Peter Taylor to "Dear Bill" 1958 Nov, 2 TMss (w/autograph corrections). 33 pp. (Box 1)
    - "Guests" 1958 Dec 3, Galley Proof. 44 pp. (Box 1)
    - "Gwendolyn's Divorce" n.d., 3 TMss (w/autograph corrections). 34 pp. (Box 1)
    - "In the Micro District" [1976?], TMs. 48 pp. (Box 1)
    - "In the Micro District" n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 48 pp. (Box 1)
    - "In the Micro District," accompanied by TLS, Fiction Department, The New Yorker, to Peter Taylor, 1 p. 1976 Sep 10, TMs (electrostatic copy). 48 pp. (Box 1)
    - "Lee in the Mountains" n.d., AMs. 1 p. (Box 1)
    - "Like the Sad Heart of Ruth," in The New Republic 1941 Dec 8, Magazine. 2 pp. (Box 1)
    - "Mrs. Billingsby's Wine" 1966 Nov 14, Galley Proof. 11 p. (Box 1)
    - "The Narrower View" n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 30 pp. (Box 1)
    - "The Other Times," from The New Yorker 1957 Feb 23, Magazine clipping. 19 pp. (Box 1)
    - "An Overwhelming Question," from Miss Leonora When Last Seen n.d., Clipping (electrostatic copy). 18 pp. (Box 1)
    - "A Pair of Bright-Blue Eyes" and "Reservations," from The New Yorker 1958, 1961, Magazine clipping. 26 pp. (Box 1)
    - "The Party" and "The Lady is Civilized" in River 1937 Mar-Apr, Magazines. 8 pp. (Box 1)
    - "The Pilgrim Sons" n.d., 3 AMss. 5 pp. (Box 1)
    - "The Pilgrim Sons," (originally titled "Fellow Travellers, Old Style") n.d., 2 TMss (w/autograph corrections). 6 pp. (Box 1)
    - "Porte-Cochere," from The New Yorker 1949 July 16, Magazine clipping (electrostatic copy). 4 pp. (Box 1)
    - "A Sentimental Journey," from The New Yorker 1955 Mar 12, n.d., Magazine clipping & TMs (incomplete). 16 pp. (Box 1)
    - "A Strange Story," from Miss Leonora When Last Seen n.d., Clipping (electrostatic copy). 30 pp. (Box 1)
    - "Sweat" 1967 Jun 12, TMs (w/autograph corrections). 9 pp. (Box 2)
    - "The Unforgivable," (originally titled "In Mero Proper") n.d., AMs. 5 pp. (Box 2)
    - "The Unforgivable," (originally titled "The Public School Boy" and "In Mero Proper") 1957 Aug 14, n.d., 2 TMss (w/autograph corrections). 27 pp. (Box 2)
    - "The Unforgivable," accompanied by TLS, "W.M." to Peter Taylor" 1957 Nov 13, Galley Proof. 19 pp. (Box 2)
    - "The Unforgivable," from The New Yorker 1950 Jan 25, Magazine clipping. 15 pp. (Box 2)
    - "Venus, Cupid, Folly and Time," from the Kenyon Review 1958 Spring, Magazine clipping. 34 pp. (Box 2)
    - "A Walled Garden," from Happy Families are All Alke n.d., Clipping (electrostatic copy). 6 pp. (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Manuscript Pages n.d., TMs, AMs. 5 pp. (Box 2)
    - The Collected Stories of Peter Taylor n.d., Galley Proof. 212 pp. (Box 2)
    - Happy Families Are All Alike n.d., Page Proof. 92 pp. (Box 2)
    - A Long Fourth and Other Stories n.d., Galley Proof. 73 pp. (Box 3)
    - A Long Fourth and Other Stories n.d., Page Proof. 57 pp. (Box 3)
    - In the Miro District and Other Stories, 2 folders 1976 July 22, TMs (setting copy) (w/autograph corrections). 187 pp. (Box 3)
    - In the Miro District and Other Stories 1976 Nov 13, Galley Proof (w/autograph corrections). 69 pp. (Box 3)
    - In the Miro District and Other Stories 1976 Nov 29, Page Proof (w/autograph corrections). 108 pp. (Box 3)
    - The Widows of Thornton n.d., Page Proof. 103 pp. (Box 4)
  - Subseries B: Plays
    - "The Death of a Kinsman" n.d., TMs (carbon). 48 pp. (Box 4)
    - "Eminent Domain" n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 5 pp. (Box 4)
    - "Family Pieces" n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 4 pp. (Box 4)
    - The Game Room n.d., TMss (carbon). 96 pp. (Box 4)
    - "A Later Plane" n.d., AMs, notebook. 6 pp. (Box 4)
    - "A Later Plane" n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 6 pp. (Box 4)
    - "A Later Plane" n.d., 2 TMss (1 w/autograph corrections). 7 pp. (Box 4)
    - A Stand in the Moutains, (previously titled "The Girl from Forked Deer") n.d., TMs (electrostatic copy). 93 pp. (Box 4)
    - A Stand in the Moutains n.d., TMs. 183 pp. (Box 4)
    - A Stand in the Moutains n.d., TMs (electrostatic copy). 171 p. (Box 4)
    - A Stand in the Moutains, incomplete n.d., TMs (electrostatic copy). 31 p. (Box 4)
    - The Southern Colony n.d., TMs (carbon). 190 pp. (Box 4)
    - Tennessee Day in St. Louis n.d., 2 TMss (carbons) (w/autograph corrections). 228 pp. (Box 5)
    - Tennessee Day in St. Louis n.d., TMs (carbon & mimeo) (w/autograph corrections). 212 pp. (Box 5)
    - Tennessee Day in St. Louis, 2 folders n.d., TMs. 234 pp. (Box 5)
    - Tennessee Day in St. Louis, Act I n.d., TMs (carbon). 31 p. (Box 5)
    - Title Unkown n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 12 pp. (Box 5)
    - Presences, 2 folders n.d., Setting Copy. 378 pp. (Box 5)
    - Presences 1972 Aug 3, Galley Proof (master) (w/autograph corrections). 80 pp. (Box 5)
    - Presences 1973, Galley Proof (author's duplicate). 80 pp. (Box 6)
    - Presences 1972 Sep 12, Page Proof (w/autograph corrections). 114 pp. (Box 6)
  - Subseries C: Poetry
    - "Blows" n.d., 2 TMss (w/autograph corrections). 2 pp. (Box 6)
    - "An Entry From His Journal," from an unknown work n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 4 pp. (Box 6)
    - "The Hand of Emmagene" n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 19 pp. (Box 6)
    - "The Hand of Emmagene" n.d., 3 TMss (w/autograph corrections). 4 pp. (Box 6)
    - "In the Miro District" n.d., AMs. 4 pp. (Box 6)
    - "In the Miro District," 2 folders n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 20 pp. (Box 6)
    - "The Instruction of a Mistress" n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 6 pp. (Box 6)
    - "Knowing" and "His Other Life" n.d., 2 TMss (w/autograph corrections).pp. (Box 6)
    - "The Megalopolitans" n.d., 3 TMss (1 w/autograph corrections). 21 p. (Box 6)
    - "The Megalopolitans," (originally titled "Crossing the Charles) n.d., TMs (fragments, some w/autograph corrections). 23 pp. (Box 6)
    - "The Megalopolitans" n.d., 3 TMss (1 w/autograph corrections, electrostatic copies). 18 pp. (Box 6)
    - "Mrs. Border's Retirement" n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 2 pp. (Box 6)
    - "New Dust" n.d., TMs. 3 pp. (Box 6)
    - "Peach Tree Gone Wild in the Lane" n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 1 p. (Box 6)
    - "A Tale of Two Cities" n.d., TMs (w/autograph corrections). 25 pp. (Box 6)
    - "Three Heroine" n.d., 3 TMss (2 w/autograph corrections, 1 electrostatic copy). 19 pp. (Box 6)
    - Poems n.d., TMs (electrostatic copies). 28 pp. (Box 6)
    - Poems n.d., 32 TMss (some w/autograph corrections). 28 pp. (Box 6)
    - Poems n.d., Page Proof (incomplete). 19 pp. (Box 6)
    - "Wires Home" and "Chickless" 1975 Jun 5, 2 TMss. 7 pp. (Box 6)
  - Subseries D. Notebooks"
    - "Stand in the Mountains," "Second Chance," "Emminent Domain," "The Second Going," and "The People that Believe in the World" 1973, Play Notebook.pp. (Box 7)
    - "The Whistler," "The Dreamer," "Family Scene," "The Senator," and "Family Pieces" n.d., Play Notebook.pp. (Box 7)
    - "Mrs. Border's Resignation," "Two Ghosts," "A Missing Person," and "A Father and Son" n.d., Play Notebook.pp. (Box 7)
    - "The Fortress," and "Second Going" n.d., Play Notebook.pp. (Box 7)
    - "Three Heroines," "Art of Love," "Hand of Mary Jo (Emmagene)," "I Had," "Rivals," "The Purse," "His Other Life," and "My Allergy, My Darling" n.d., Poetry Notebook.pp. (Box 7)
    - "All Kinds of Money," "Tolliver Campbell," "A Story of More Woe," "A Stand in the Mountains," "Peace," "The Enslaved," "Old Soldiers," and "Megalopolitans," (Bicentennial)" n.d., Poetry Notebook.pp. (Box 7)
    - "Paying Guest," "Files," "Upon the Return of a Former Student," and "In the Miro District" n.d., Poetry Notebook.pp. (Box 7)
    - "Scenes from My Life," "The Will," and "Eminent Domain" n.d., Notebook (Short Story and Play): .pp. (Box 7)
  - Subseries E: Miscellaneous
    - Randall Jarrell: 1914-1965, edited by Robert Lowell, Peter Taylor, and Robert Penn Warren n.d., Galley Proof. 102 pp. (Box 7)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Personal Correspondence, including w/Robert Giroux and Paul Engle 1948-1949, 4 items (Box 8)
  - Personal Correspondence, including w/John Casey and Allen Williams 1970-1974, 14 items (Box 8)
  - Personal Correspondence, including w/John Malcolm Brinnan 1975, 17 items (Box 8)
  - Personal Correspondence, including w/John McCutcheon, Irvin Ehrenpreis, Richard Jones and Dumas Malone 1976, 47 items (Box 8)
  - Personal Correspondence, including w/John McCutcheon, Richard Jones, Allen Tate, Ralph ellison, and John Casey 1977, 55 items (Box 8)
  - Personal Correspondence, including w/John Casey and Richard Jones n.d., 16 items (Box 8)
  - Correspondence w/ The New Yorker, includes "first reading" contracts, 2 folders 1948-1977, n.d., 111 items (Box 8)
  - Correspondence w/Random House, Harcourt Brace & Co., McDowell Obolensky, Inc., Ivan Obolensky, Inc. and Astor-Honor, Inc. (publishers) 1949-1968, n.d., 85 items (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous business correspondence 1948-1977, n.d., 37 items (Box 9)
  - Correspondence from year in Europe 1955-1956, n.d., 15 items (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous material from year in Europe 1955-1956, n.d., 27 items (Box 9)
- Series III: Printed Material
  - "Gentleman in a Dustcoat" (John Crowe Ransom) by Allen Tate, from Kenyon Alumni Bulletin 1968 Apr/Jun, 1 item (Box 9)
  - HiKA, Kenyon College Literary Magazine w/selections by PT 1939-1940, 4 items (Box 9)
  - Potomac Magazine: " The New Yorker 's Scribes in Charlottesville" and "Katherine Anne Porter & the Vanity of Excellence" 1968, 1974, 1 item (Box 9)
  - "Reelfoot's Night Riders," from Southern Sportsman 1963-1964, 5 items (Box 9)
- Series IV: Photographs
  - Photographs 1958, 1973, n.d., 5 items (Box 9)
- Series V: Miscellaneous
  - A Sad Heart at the Supermarket" by Ranall Jarrell n.d., TMss. 1 item (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous n.d., 20 items (Box 9)